Finding aid for the J. Paul Getty Museum, Getty Villa Construction Records, 1960, 1964, 1968-1986 and undated (bulk 1971-1974) IA10001
Institutional Records and Archives
- Blueline prints and architectural drawings, 1964; 1968,; 1970-1977,; undated; Series VI.; 22.4 Linear Feet (1 box, 6 flat file drawers, 2 oversize boxes)
  - Langdon and Wilson
    - Drawings
      - Reproduction of a Langdon and Wilson drawing of exterior view of Museum and environs, on heavy board, unsigned, undated (Box 1986.IA.08-30, Flatfile 1986.IA.36-5)
        [Another reproduction of this image appears in box 30, folder 2, and identifies it as originating with Langdon & Wilson]
    - Photographs of drawings
      - Photos of Langdon and Wilson blueline drawings, undated; [15 images] (Box 1986.IA.36-1, Folder 1)
      - Negatives: architectural drawings, models, aerial view, 1971; undated; [10 black-and-white photographic negatives] (Box 1986.IA.36-1)
      - Negatives of Langdon and Wilson blueline drawings, July 11, 1974; [reel of 10 images] (Box 1986.IA.36-1, Box 1)
        [Notations on the box indicate "misc. shots, incl. planting."]
      - Negatives of Langdon and Wilson blueline drawings, March 17, 1975; [reel of 14 images] (Box 1986.IA.36-1, Box 2)
        [Notations on the box indicate "drawings for plumbing/water system."]
      - Langdon and Wilson drawings: Plan of Upper Galleries and Courtyard; Plan of Colonnade Galleries; South Facade/North Facade/Transverse Section Looking North/Longitudinal Section Looking East, October 18, 1968; [3 mounted color photos] (Box 1986.IA.19-19, Folder 1)
      - Langdon and Wilson drawing/watercolor of exterior view of Museum and environs, unsigned, undated; [2 mounted color photos] (Box 1986.IA.19-19, Folder 2)
        [One of the two has on the verso: "Received by Stephen Garrett with Bob Langdon letter dated May 28, 1971 ."]
      - Color photo reproductions of Langdon and Wilson painting of J. Paul Getty Museum (aerial view), undated; [8 unmounted, 6 mounted] (Box 1986.IA.19-19, Folder 3)
      - Photo reproductions of Langdon and Wilson painting of J. Paul Getty Museum (aerial view), undated; [3 large mounted] (Box 1986.IA.19-19, Folder 4)
  - Other sources
    - Blueline Drawings
      - Museum Siting. Stephen Garrett, undated; [3 sheets] (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-31)
      - Proposed Upper Lemon Grove Parking Area (Unit 1) and Access Road from Existing Lower Parking Area. Preliminary Plan, John S. Gregory Co., Civil Engineers, September 19, 1974; [3 sheets] (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-31)
      - Untitled Blueline drawing – Retaining Wall Details. John S. Gregory Co., December 5, 1974; undated; [2 sheets] (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-31)
      - As Build Survey of Museum Bldg. and Fence Line. John S. Gregory Co., February 20, 1976 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-31)
      - Proposed Temple West of Sycamore Grove. Emmet L. Wemple and Associates, Landscape Architects, 1973 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-31)
      - Street Plans of Getty Museum Main Entrance. Emmet L. Wemple and Associates, Landscape Architects, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-31)
      - Getty Museum Main Entrance. Emmet L. Wemple and Associates, Landscape Architects, undated; [4 sheets - 1 copy each of pages 1 and 2, 2 sheets of page 3] (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-31)
      - A-1: Pacific Coast Highway Entry. Emmet L. Wemple and Associates, Landscape Architects, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-31)
      - A-2: Pacific Coast Highway Entry. Emmet L. Wemple and Associates, Landscape Architects, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-31)
      - Map of suggested priorities prepared for the Santa Monica Mountains and Seashore Urban Park Citizens Advisory Committee by Winston Salser, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-32)
      - Parking addition. Rex B. Link and Associates, May 20, 1974 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-32)
      - Roadway easement. Toups Engineering Co, April 5, 1972 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-32)
      - Driveway approach for J. Paul Getty property. VTN Los Angeles, December 8, 1971 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-32)
      - Driveway Study – J.P. Getty property. VTN Los Angeles, February 8, 1972 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-32)
      - Los Liones Drive. VTN Los Angeles, November 15, 1971 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-32)
      - J. Paul Getty Malibu Ranch. Compiled from Recorded Maps and Instruments by R. A. Stroud, July 1972; revised January 1973; [8 sheets; 2 of them taped photosheets] (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-32)
      - Topographic map of Getty Museum, from Mollenhauer, Higashi and Moore, Inc., November 1977; [3 sheets - 5 sheets sheet 1, 3 sheets sheet 2, 2 sheets sheet 3] (Flatfile 1986.IA.19-45)
        [Sheet 3 is reproduction of aerial photography by Metrex]
      - Map of Portion Allot. No. 3 Pascual Marquez in Rancho Boca de Santa Monica. Chas. Edwin Hills, undated; [2 sheets: 1 on paper, the other photographic] (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-33)
      - Preliminary Parcel Map No. 2934, January 1975; [2 unnumbered sheets: 1 map and 1 supplementary information] (Flatfile 1986.IA.19-45)
      - Parcel Map L.A. No. 2934. Prepared by John S. Gregory, 1976; [4 sheets of page 1, pages 2-4 missing] (Flatfile 1986.IA.19-45)
      - Parcel Map L.A. No. 2934. Prepared by John S. Gregory, 1976; [3 sheets of page 2, pages 1 and 3 missing] (Flatfile 1986.IA.19-45)
      - Untitled - small map of Getty property and surrounding areas. Voorheis Trindle Co., February 28, 1964 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-33)
      - Surfview Drive Easement – Plan and Profile of Storm Drain. City of Los Angeles, Voorheis – Trindle Co., undated; [6 sheets] (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-33)
      - Santa Monica Mountains Topographic Maps. City of Los Angeles, October 25, 1977 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-33)
    - Drawings
      - Garth Benton watercolor of South Porch (proposed design for typical central section), undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-34)
      - Garth Benton watercolor of Main Peristyle wall design, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-34)
      - Garth Benton watercolor of Main Peristyle wall design. Unsigned, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-34)
        [Differs from final design (?).]
      - Watercolor of Museum facade by David F. Wilkins, signed and dated; Watercolor of exterior view of arches by David F. Wilkins, signed and dated., October 17, 1968; October 11, 1971 (Flatfile 1986.IA.36-6)
      - Drawing of marble floor design (stamped Ditta P. Medici and Figlio, Roma), undated; [Pencil, colored pencil] (Flatfile 1986.IA.36-7)
      - Watercolor of exterior view of window design, mounted. Unsigned, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.36-8)
      - Drawing of a Roman Villa (possibly Villa dei Papiri), undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-35)
        [Notation in corner: "Lit. Petruzzelli-Napoli." Weber?]
    - Photographs of drawings
      - Schematic Drawings and Preliminary Graphic Schedule, from John Follis and Associates, undated (Box 1986.IA.08-29, Folder 1)
      - Negative print (?) of unknown blueline drawing (Proposed Drainage Easement), with Letter of Transmittal from Emmet Wemple, Landscape Architect and Associates, undated (Box 1986.IA.08-29, Folder 2)
      - 3 transparencies of architectural drawings, including the Stephen Garrett Villa Siting drawing (Flat File 29) and the drawing of the Villa Dei Papiri (Flat File 36), undated (Box 1986.IA.08-29, Folder 3)
      - Photographs, color transparencies, and negatives of drawings and watercolors of J. Paul Getty Museum by David F. Wilkins, Langdon and Wilson, Garth Benton, and Ditta P. Medici and Figlio, undated (Box 1986.IA.08-29, Folder 4)
        [These are photos of originals which are housed in Flatfile folders 28, 32, 33, and 34.]
      - Mounted color photo of watercolor of exterior view of arches, signed and dated Dave Wilkins, October 11, 1971 (Box 1986.IA.36-2, Folder 1)
- Models, 1972-1973; 1987,; undated; Series VII.; 3.5 Linear Feet (2 oversize boxes)
  The models precede the images of the models.
  The records consist of architectural models, notes, and photographs, 1972-1973, 1987, undated, of the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa). The models represent the Decorative Arts Period Rooms of the new Villa museum. The photographs are images of the architectural models.
  - Note giving information about the Decorative Arts Period Room models ("Made by Jansen, either Paris or New York c. 1972, artist unknown"), May 18, 1987 (Box 1987.IA.02-1, Folder 1)
  - Models of Decorative Arts period Rooms: Fourteen wall panel models constructed of plywood and cardboard, 1972 (Box 1987.IA.02-1)
  - Three models of Floors [?] of Decorative Arts Period Rooms: rooms 210, 211, and unspecified, March 20, 1973 (Box 1987.IA.02-2)
  - Photographs of architectural models, undated; [21 black and white images, 4 color photographs] (Box 1986.IA.08-29, Folder 5)
    [Some images are duplicated.]
- Photographs of museum and museum construction, 1969-1974; 1976,; undated; (bulk 1971-1974); Series VIII.; 5 Linear Feet (1 flat file folder, 3 photo albums, 3 oversize boxes, 1 box)
  Aerial site photos precede photos of construction progress and completed museum. The construction progress albums precede the "paste-ups". The photos in the albums have been assembled chronologically, the "paste-ups" are in numerical order. Several images of the completed museum are listed at the end.
  The records consist of photographs of the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa) site, photos of the museum construction, and photos taken shortly after the museum's completion, dating 1969-1974, 1976, undated (bulk 1971-1974). The site photos are oversize aerial photos of the Villa site, taken before the beginning of construction, in 1968 and 1969. The majority of the photographic prints are either in three albums (ca. 800-1200 photos) or are loose. The photos in the albums are frequently dated and captioned on the back. A number of copies of photos from the albums have been pasted together to form panoramas, and were assembled by Stephen Garrett to show J. Paul Getty the progress of the construction project. These "paste-ups" are on cardboard backing with captions.
  - Aerial site photos
    - Aerial photograph of the Getty Malibu property by the Metrex Aerial Surveys Co., August 9, 1968; [3 copies] (Flatfile 1986.IA.19-46)
      [One copy has strips of colored paper and typed labels highlighting Getty land and landmarks surrounding Getty land.]
    - Aerial photograph with caption "Preliminary Study for Lower Grove Site, Museum Building shown per Schematic LG-3." From Langdon and Wilson, November 1969 (Flatfile 1986.IA.08-36)
      [The photograph has a graphic addition of the proposed museum building added.]
  - Stephen Garrett's photos of construction progress and completed museum
    - Progress photos, February 2, 1971-March 23, 1972 (Box 1987.IA.24-1)
    - Progress photos, April 12, 1972-August 16, 1973 (Box 1987.IA.24-2)
    - Progress photos, August 22, 1973-July 25, 1974; undated (Box 1987.IA.24-3)
    - Construction progress photos, "paste-ups":
      - 1-10, undated (1940s-1950s); July 1969 (Box 1987.IA.24-5, Folder 1)
      - 11-15, March 1970; January 1971,; undated (Box 1987.IA.24-5, Folder 2)
      - 17-20, March-April 1971; December 1971,; undated (Box 1987.IA.24-5, Folder 3)
      - 21-25, May-June 1971; February 1972,; undated (Box 1987.IA.24-5, Folder 4)
      - 25-29, June-August 1971; February 1972 (Box 1987.IA.24-5, Folder 5)
      - 30-35, August-November 1971 (Box 1987.IA.24-5, Folder 6)
      - 36-39, November-December 1971 (Box 1987.IA.24-5, Folder 7)
      - 50-57, April-December 1971 (Box 1987.IA.24-5, Folder 8)
      - 58-63, December 1971-February 1972 (Box 1987.IA.24-5, Folder 9)
      - 64-73, February-June 1972 (Box 1987.IA.24-6, Folder 1)
      - 74-83, June 1972 (Box 1987.IA.24-6, Folder 2)
      - 84-95, July-August 1972 (Box 1987.IA.24-6, Folder 3)
      - 96-104, August-September 1972 (Box 1987.IA.24-6, Folder 4)
      - 105-115, September-October 1972 (Box 1987.IA.24-6, Folder 5)
      - 116-126, November 1972 (Box 1987.IA.24-6, Folder 6)
      - 127-137, November 1972-January 1973 (Box 1987.IA.24-6, Folder 7)
      - 138-147, January-March 1973 (Box 1987.IA.24-6, Folder 8)
      - 148-149, D, J and unidentified, March 1973; undated (Box 1987.IA.24-6, Folder 9)
    - Photos of completed Museum by Julius Shulman: letter from Shulman, June 11, 1976, re. photos of Sutton place (not present) from 1964., and photocopies of photographs, circa 1976 (Box 1987.IA.24-4, Folder 1)
    - Color transparencies of completed Museum by Julius Shulman, circa 1974 (Box 1987.IA.24-4, Folder 2)
    - Photos of completed Museum by Julius Shulman, circa 1974 (Box 1987.IA.24-4, Folder 3)
    - Oversize photos of museum construction and completed museum, of unidentified origin, undated (Box 1986.IA.36-2, Folder 2)
- Oral and written histories of the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa) design and construction, 1972; 1980,; 1986; Series IX.; 0.1 Linear Feet (3 audiocassettes and 2 folders)
  The audiocassettes precede the transcripts and book pages.
  The records consist of audiocassettes, notes, and printed material, dated 1972, 1980, and 1986, that include two recordings of lecture/conversations about the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa) building project, one by Stephen Garrett, and the other (with typed transcript) by Norman Neuerburg. In addition, there are a few pages of a book proposal by Neuerburg with some introductory pages giving autobiographical material and background on the project.
  - Cassette audiotape of Stephen Garrett talking about slides of the construction of the Getty Museum, recorded, Fall 1980 (Box 1987.IA.24-4)
  - Cassette audiotapes: "Norman Neuerburg on the Design of the Getty Museum," conversation during walking tour Neuerburg, 1986; [2 tapes] (Box 1987.IA.03-1)
  - Typed transcripts of Norman Neuerburg on the Design of the Getty Museum" walking tour: one 46 page draft with handwritten corrections and one 45 page final copy, 1986 (Box 1987.IA.03-1)
  - Norman Neuerburg manuscript: draft of a "Monograph on the Architecture of the J. Paul Getty Museum,", May 29, 1972 (Box 1986.IA.08-29, Folder 6)
    [Includes an outline of the proposed book, as well as ca. 2 pages of the manuscript, which includes autobiographical material. Appendices are: "Proposal for Garden Display Room," credited to Neuerburg, Emmet Wemple and Denis Kurutz; "Thoughts On Museum Installation: memorandum" by Neuerburg; and "Villa Display Room: proposal" by Neuerburg. ]
- Printed matter and notes, 1960; undated; Series X.; 0.1 Linear Feet (1 box)
  The printed materials precede the notes.
  Records consist of notes and printed materials, dating from 1960 and undated, related to research and planning for the J. Paul Getty Museum (Villa). Museum staff member Gillian Wilson seems to have been the creator of the majority of the notes, while the printed materials was created by the Guggenheim Museum and presumably was retained to serves as samples of the types of ephemeral introductory material produced by other museums.
  - Printed matter from the Guggenheim Museum, 1960; undated (Box 1986.IA.08-29, Folder 7)
  - Printed matter and 1 page of handwritten notes (unsigned) re. sprinkler systems, undated (Box 1986.IA.08-29, Folder 8)
  - Various handwritten and typed notes re. museum construction and administration. Unsigned, except for 7 pages of notes marked "Gillian Wilson – Confidential,", undated (Box 1986.IA.08-29, Folder 9)